In this lesson we're going to explore the TypeScript compiler, which is also called TSC.
Understanding how the compiler works is essential because it's going to turn your TypeScript
code into executable JavaScript that can run in a browser or Node.js.
So what exactly is the TypeScript compiler?
So the compiler converts TypeScript, which is .ts files to JavaScript.js files.
It also performs type checking and generates target compatible.js.
So the compiler TSC is a pretty important tool that does two important things.
It checks our code for type errors and it generates TypeScript and which can run anywhere
that JavaScript runs.
But let's actually see how it works and practice.
So I've just got a command prompt here and I've created a blank folder.
Now first of all you need to make sure you have TypeScript installed on your computer.
So you can do NPM, install, and then G, the global flag, TypeScript.
That's going to go off and it's just going to install TypeScript.
Now to check that's been working fine, you can do TSC, which is the name of the compiler,
hyphen, hyphen, and then version.
Now I've got version currently, 5.93, so just checks that things are installed correctly.
Now what we can do is we can create ourselves a little type example, TypeScript file.
We can do it in any editor, for example, we can just fire up a text editor like notepad.
So I'm just going to create a new file, we call it call it hello.ts, and I'm going
to open that in notepad.
So here's my file.
So let's just do very simple TypeScript, so we can say let greeting, and we can find it
as a string, which we can do by colon and then string.
I don't worry too much about this at the moment, we had card this just yet.
So just this is a way we define a variable as a string.
I mean, it can define a value for that.
So we can say hello, JavaScript, hello, JavaScript, hello, TypeScript, and then we can do
console, a log, and output our greeting.
So nice and simple.
Let's just save that file, and it's so saved at, is that test t file, I'm going to change
it from our ts.txt file by doing run, hello.ts.txt to hello.ts, so now we just have hello.ts.
Now to compile this and convert it into JavaScript, we just do tsc, tsc, and then the name
of the file.
So hello.ts, wait a moment, and nothing particularly looks like
it happens, but if we have a look at our folder, here it is, we have a js file, hello.js.
We can open that in Notepad, and hey presto, it looks identical, a nearly identical, but
notice the difference in the fact that we don't have that colon string, we have just normal
JavaScript.
We can just take this JavaScript in a normal way, and execute node or browser.
So as you can see, TypeScript types are removed during compilation, and they're only used
for development type checks, but it can spit out about a JavaScript.
Now that tsc commands comes with a whole load of different options, and if we do tsc,
my space and hyphen hyphen help, we can see it comes with all these options.
The ones that I would recommend that we need is the one here, target, because it decides,
I said, which JavaScript language version we want to emit, and we recommend that we do
at ES6, because all browsers as support that, ES6, and the other switch that's useful
is this one hyphen hyphen strict, because you want to make sure that we enable all the
strict type checking options, rather than just some of them.
So we can come into here, and we can do tsc, to want to recompile with options of ES6, we
also want the strict, so hyphen hyphen strict, and then the name of our actual files, so
we can do hello dot ts, that's going to input the JavaScript in these with these options.
This is the ones we recommend, we have some perhaps you want to maybe put it in a little
batch file, or just have this as part of your build process.
The other useful command line switch is watch, so we do tsc, hyphen hyphen watch, is then
going to watch for the changes of a particular file, so if we do hello dot ts, and then
put it into a watch mode, so if we then come into here, or let's open up our ts file, just
bring it up here, open that we have, let's open it with visual studio code, and now if
we decide to change from hello TypeScript, let's say, hello TypeScript tsc, then save
the file, now if we go to our js file, we automatically get the compile version tsc any
changes.
We've learned about the TypeScript compiler out of the very basics, and some useful
options. In the next lesson we're going to learn how to use the TypeScript compiler in
Visual Studio Code, which is probably the world's most popular editor for doing TypeScript.